the center
defined as a focal point around which
any object revolves
we however define the center to mean
much more
it's where knowledge and ideas form a
nucleus
where dreams intersect with possibility
a starting point from which your life
can go anywhere
this is how we at columbia business
school define the center
the very center of business
here you'll find the center of
opportunity
where world-class academics open doors
to the world's most dynamic place of
business
new york city come learn at the center
of knowledge
where top academic minds do leading edge
research
on the latest business trends and
innovations
be at the center of access where today's
titans of industry spend
every day face time with students and
faculty
discover the center of convergence where
finance
fashion media healthcare high tech and
all industries intersect join the center
of community
where high achievers the world over
share an open exchange of ideas and
perspectives
dream at the center of entrepreneurship
where an ivy league business degree
gives you entree to the world's fastest
growing startup environment
and reach the center of global impact
where a network of over
40 000 alumni are creating real change
across the planet the very center of
business
where all potential converges where
chances for success
revolve all around a place you just
won't find anywhere else
come find yourself here at the very
center of business
columbia business school
foreign
live streaming from columbia business
school in new york city my name is bruce
town
welcome to the final session of the 13th
columbia china business conference
home to value investing columbia
business school is at the forefront of
the theoretical development and
practices
of value investing given the average
change in global dynamics
and market uncertainties what are the
potential advancements
on unwavering fundamentals of value
investing
how should practitioners realize value
investing in china
joining us today are professor bruce
greenward and mr lee liu
professor bruce greenward is the
founding director of the helpful center
for graham dodd
investing at columbia business school
his leading voice in value investing
mr lilu is the founder and chairman of
himalaya capital
a multi-billion dollar investment firm
that primarily focuses on long-term
investment opportunities
in asia and the us he's a distinguished
alumnus of colombia and mr leeloo
currently serves as a member of the
board of trustees of columbia university
professor greenward routinely wins
plotters for his classes
and has trained a generation of value
investors including lisa lillu himself
recently liu has in-depth knowledge
about the chinese market
his insights are trusted by investment
legends like buffett
and monger now imagine yourself stepping
into the most overcrowded investment
classroom
at one of the best business schools
across the globe welcome professor
greenwood
and mr lee okay thank you
um i think this is going to be a rare
privilege for
everybody i've known lee liu now for
more than 20 years and not only is he a
great investor but he's a great
conversationalist so why don't we just
start out
uh by talking about how your investment
philosophy has changed because value
investing
is after all always an evolving field
since you began the field literally i
think i would say
25 years ago 20 years ago or like 28 now
time
so how has it evolved so how have you
been influenced by people like
uh charlie munger and so on yeah go
ahead
well so uh before i started i just want
to uh
first of all thank you for all the
organizers of this
great conferences i mean i look at the
uh
the speakers are just really
unbelievable so
uh the uh the quality of the student
has dramatically improved since i was a
student there so
thank you for all for that wonderful
work of putting together these great
conferences
and it just really gave me such a
pleasure to be on the same panel with my
professor
bruce greenwald in fact i got into uh
uh the this field really because of
uh professor greenwald's class um
i think you know basically you
you got uh buffet to come to uh speak
to a student really
roughly 28 years ago and it was really
out of that first lecture that i really
got into this field so thank you so much
and of course i later as a
business group student
i took all of the courses that professor
greenblatt offered and learned a great
deal and made a lot of money too so
thank you yeah so the philosophy is that
uh it it is it is you know
relatively simple uh the practice is
really hard
um so i wouldn't say the philosophy
really
evolved all that much for me
before i got really exposed to value
investing through
buffett's lecture at a bruce greenwald's
class
but i think my whole approach to life
was
pretty much a set along similar lines
and so there's not much of a jump for me
the idea of buying something at a
discount
or something that really worth more is
just is simply intelligent
so i would say almost all intelligent
investing involves some kind of a value
investing
and now the difference is is that your
focus on values evolves
over time and two different individuals
they tend to focus
different areas of that
for me when i first started
as a value investor this is now 27
28 years ago when i lost my first stock
i don't really know much about uh
business uh i i know i was born and
raised in
uh china during the uh cultural
revolution there was
not much of a private business over
market economy
back then so i have to learn everything
new
uh so uh at the beginning
uh obviously if look for value uh
primarily
uh on the balance sheet in the in the
classic uh style of benjamin graham
looking for a cigarette butt uh looking
for the elastic off
basically not looking for statistically
cheap
businesses and ignore what the business
really is
and that served me well and that over
time i evolved
into understanding smaller businesses
and because i was just intensively
curious about how business run
so much so actually i involved into
health funding or co-creating
a dozen those early stage startup
companies
and that experience has taught me a lot
about
how businesses what constituted a good
or bad of mediocre businesses
and so over time evolved into looking
for
really good businesses small maybe but
really good businesses
uh and then that
leads me to look for good businesses in
asia and eventually
for businesses was enduring competitive
advantage
uh with a long uh growth trajectory
ahead
and so the places where we're looking
for a bad
evolves over time but the basic
philosophy have
pretty much remained the same it's just
our core competence
expended over time
now i have been very fortunate to be
influenced
at the very beginning by the investment
giant
buffett and and later on i was
really really lucky it was just a streak
of uh stroke of a whole lot
that he can't even make it up uh in
fictions
that i uh strike a good
um connection with uh charlie munger
and he become an investor
2003 2004
and we've been partners since then
basically he has been a mentor
a investor a business partner and a
great friend
all those years and for many many years
we've been we have dinner every tuesday
night
that's what is my version of a tuesday
night with charlie
uh every week uh that lasted
for years until just right around the
pandemic
and we talk a lot more so obviously i
had a great deal of influence by him
but i have to say that the greatest
influence from charlie was really beyond
just
investment it was he was more of a role
model in the way he conducted himself in
real life
now i think for every profession
everybody
it is wonderful to have role models in
life
and often we find role models
among the imminent dead
because it's safer so it's pretty risky
to pick a role model and still still
alive
and that i always have a risk of
disappointing
but in my case i got really really lucky
in the sense
that my role model never failed
in instead of continuing to inspire me
right into his 97th year basically
and so mostly it's really basic his
attitude towards
life and his ability to keep
equanimity in a sense in the face of up
and downs
successful setbacks and i witnessed
quite a bit of them
over the 17 years or so we've been
working closely
um maintain that rational composure
commonsensical approach to all problems
investment in our life that is
extraordinary hard
and it is a bit of um
against very natural tendencies
and i've really washed the clothes up
close and personal
how charlie have conducted himself
and it is in that regard that he is
probably the most influential person in
my life
and i have been very very lucky in that
regard
okay um so in this concentration
instead of now investing in great
businesses
um can you be specific about
what kind of business you look for what
are the characteristics
of a great business in particular what
detail characteristics you look for and
how you put a value on those businesses
yeah well uh great
businesses are the ones who really have
above average
returners as best at capital
but that kind of businesses socially
attract
imitators competitors everybody wants to
have
evolved average return to every invested
capital
and so truly good business is the one
who can fend off
competitors we can really have enduring
competitive advantage and cap that
higher than average return on invested
capital
and hopefully also have a long runway of
continuous
growth those are the businesses we're
looking for
and they could really come in all
industries in all
shapes and forms um but they're rare
they're really really rare to have a
business that generates above average
returns
over a long time on a compounded fashion
this again is really against the natural
orders of things
it really only a small slice of all
businesses belong to that category
so if you're really lucky enough to
really find one of those
long-term compounders all you have to do
is really
uh to own them and own them for the
longest period of time
now it helps when you really buy them
at the time when they were happen to be
treated
at a discount to a very intrinsic value
so that if you were wrong about them you
won't lose
money and if you're right you're having
more returns over time
but over the longest period of time if
you do own them through the up and downs
your return roughly approximates
basically
the actual business return to the actual
capital we invested in the business
itself over the long term
the two to really converge pretty
closely
and so understanding and studying the
nature of that business with
the dynamic but competition is of
really the most important thing as the
investor and
as a student of the business and as i
said
there isn't really a set of things uh
that really
make them that way every business really
builds
their fortress uh slightly differently
and you just have to really actually be
honest with yourself and study from
every possible angles
until you're really convinced that the
azure they're currently enjoying
uh enjoying truly
enduring and they truly have a long
runway ahead of them
and if they proved to be exactly as you
predicted over the years
we really want to really stay on them
through the up and down they can mean
not to be really this way uh easily
okay can i actually uh talk a little bit
about
those businesses i mean in limiting
competition
and i think charlie munger is the master
at this you're really interested in
moats
that is the barriers to entry into the
business because it's keeping people out
that's going to limit
competition if you think about a moat
there are probably two elements to that
mode so think of it from the point of
view of a
company trying to get into the business
one
is economies of scale how big do you
have to get
how big a market share do you have to
capture in order to be viable
as a competitor so in automobiles in the
global automobile market it's really
large
and if you get one to two percent share
you're going to be fine
in other markets like for example local
distribution of caffeinated
soft drinks you got to get to 20 to 25
of the market to support uh the
infrastructure that you need
uh and to compete so the first thing is
economies of scale and the second thing
i think and again i'm
sort of thinking about charlie munger
here is how hard is it to get that
mortgage chair which is all about
customer captivity in a contested
environment where
unique technology will help you with
that and so on so suppose
you got to get to 25 share we know for
caffeinated soft drinks
that two tenths of a percent share
changes hands every year
in a contested market so to get to 25
you're talking about 125 year mode
do you do a calculation like that for
the companies you're looking at
you look at those two elements
explicitly
well that and more okay then what's the
more
the skill is important uh
in there actually there is a scale
economy
in those businesses uh not everything
actually has a skill economy
so sometimes that the skill becomes a
contract point make it actually more
difficult
to really manage um right but
in a scalar economy uh that
the scale does really become a
competitive advantage
um and then but but the dynamic would
have changed
after a certain scale the information
automobile this
interesting example you know what
happens in
different phases of the industry um
the uh the the
the uh consumer uh aside
is also important in a sense that
if you have um quite a bit of
uh uh consumer addiction
which was certain products and brand
loyalty obviously that is important
and they're good for a long time until
they're not good
um things do change new product
categories would have come along
and run get tired and owed not
refreshed need for new generations
really don't like to have the same taste
as their parents and grandparents so
that's really the most
interesting aspect of businesses is
is what is only constant is the constant
change
all great business changes over time
and i absolutely know business it can
really
remain that competitive edge for
forever but some of the business really
can keep it
for a very very very long time
and of course when it changes it's
really
upon the management team to be able
to really we allocate capital towards
those businesses actually now we enjoy
a robust competitive definition now
taking example with berkshire
you know starting out as a lousy
businesses losing businesses
of texas in new england
and warren and charlie skillfully really
took the last
bit of the cash flow and skillfully
invested
in some other businesses really on the
right
side of the trajectory but over time
some of those businesses
began to lose its competitive advantage
and then they
took their capital and they allocated to
the ones that
so obviously the management capability
of allocating capital
also plays a very important role
and of course that the culture of
a a company
in the industry that's rapidly changing
so that you always a few step ahead of
your competitors
which allows you to always observing on
the edge
that also becomes uh enduring
competitive advantage if that culture
endures
so in every specific businesses
what really make them successful are
very very different
and they change over time and so
that is the most fascinating aspect of
of the competitive dynamics and
also the most fascinating aspect of
being an investor
well how do you today as of today
how do you do this differently would you
say for most other investors
are there things that you look at
specifically
are there ways that you approach
companies now i'll tell you the thing
that when i
started investing with you and i'm
honored to say that i made a lot of
money
doing it that appealed to me was what
you mentioned
in your introduction which is small but
small businesses
are or small markets are necessarily
markets we have to get a big share
uh because one firm can dominate and
that's not something that most
investors look at so in what other ways
do you do things differently
from most other value investors and
investors
yeah well you're right you're investing
with me
or you begin to invest thank god you're
still with me
so thank you for continuing to trust in
confidence
uh no back then we were looking for a
smaller business because those the
business i feel i can understand them
and as we evolve we begin to look for
bigger
businesses that we can also understand
that bigger business does come with a
whole set of advantages
that if they are right in a sense um
they also come in with a whole bunch of
problems and so
we're not really looking not just big or
medium or small
size is is one consideration but it's
not in the most important
uh it's certainly not a determining
factors when we're looking for
businesses
there are big businesses because of a
certain dynamic
dynamics are still growing at a robust
pace
that are becoming even more entrenched
as they become bigger and they still
have long runs of
growth so that just exists
you know the most recent phenomena of
the
technology platform because of the
network
network effect some of the business of
fitting that characteristics
now they don't necessarily always grow
forever
but they have been growing for a long
long time they're likely to continue
for some time and so just the
size itself uh is certainly not the most
determining factor by
yeah but then what other dimensions do
you do things differently today than
other investors who are less successful
i don't spend my time studying 100
people doing that
we spend most of our time study uh
industries studying specific companies
we're looking for the ones we're already
successful try to
answer what really make them successful
can that success be continued
and some of the time we we have answers
and some of the time we don't
we just continue to really study them
and
continue edit until we have an answer i
think one thing that really
that is always important for us is
this um intellectual uh honesty
basically knowing that we really don't
know
um but we do know and what we don't
in other words if you claim a
circle of confidence you have to
understand the ash of the confidence
you have to know what is false and what
is close
you have to be very honest with yourself
uh
so we really insist on
knowing inside and out a particular
businesses and
to the point we're able to predict is
outcome
for example in the next 10 years at
least i want to know
that the worst case scenario what the
business
would look like 10 years from now and so
we do have a long-term
horizon in terms we can't really predict
it forever
but i want to see whether i can predict
with a very high degree of competency
90 percent of confidence that
at a minimum what the business would
look like
in 10 years given all different
contingencies
and so and and
most of the time we don't have an answer
and we just keep
studying and keep at it and sometimes we
study for years and years before
we see okay we really get it and then
we wait for price to come to our
striking zone
and a lot of the time they don't and so
that
makes our selection very very difficult
and so when we do select them we tend to
really own them for a very very long
time
because the businesses they're really
good
um and we really fully understand
are very rare you know how do you mean
when you really do you understand that
so anything that we would own we would
buy
a lot more as they go down and
how do you start yeah if they go down
fifty percent is sixty percent seventy
right
we buy more so that really gives you
a measure of our definition of whether
we understand them
okay so what about the market today i
mean it seems
highly valued i mean if you look at
fixed income it seems unprecedented
uh that said uh does the market today
remind you of any historical periods
you've lived through
in good ways or bad and would you have
advice for anybody on how to navigate
well we usually don't study too much
about the market
except when they're really extreme and
this is what happens to be one of those
more extreme period of time
it is truly in many ways somewhere in
unchartered territories
uh the amount of liquidity that's been
printed
and the level of interest rate
um and also the slow pace of the growth
all of those are quite really remarkable
uh in this time so how do you really
deal with them
um we don't
necessarily think that history will
repeat
and so every time is slightly different
instead of
guessing the patterns of history and
whether they
repeat we focus on selecting
companies that can really lift through
the thick and thin
um whatever the environment
business will continue somebody would do
well
we just want really investing in those
companies
was incapable of dealing with those
extraordinary set of uncertainties and
i'll be doing fine
and how much is management a part of
that and how do you
look for managements that have that
capability
well in a lot of the companies uh the
management will make
big differences the culture of those
management we're produced will make a
big differences
but in the small set of experiences and
management really matters almost
nothing but the best the strings of
business sell
really has a dynamic of his own
that really almost anybody can run it
and run it
well relatively now those
businesses are really rare they're not
that many you can probably put them in
one hand or two hand
and so each again i come back to the
situation
each time is different you have to
really
look for each specific company company
in specific ways
and ask all kinds of appropriate
questions and study them over a long
period of time in order to really
honestly say that you actually
understand them understand them enough
you can predict
the outcome in 10 years even given all
the up and downs in the macro
environment
so you've lived through in your 23 years
running himalaya
a number of major financial crisis the
asia crisis
in 97 the tech bust in 2000
the financial crisis in 2008 and
actually last year the code 19
are situation specific things you learn
about managements or companies that you
look for
in those crises yeah
well uh so as you said
my 24 years of managing him like capital
we have gone through several of those
big crisis each time when that happens
um it was built as once in a century
crisis it probably was except it happens
uh on the time frame of every five to
ten years
so the financial
market boom and bust is has been
a constant phenomenon since the
beginning of the financial market
uh several hundred years ago and and it
was
driven by human nature as long as human
nature remain that way
it would never change it will always be
with us
now as a product of evolution
we human are basically
i run not necessarily in a very rational
way
now we're we're very good at
rationalization but we're really not
very good at being rational
uh so so
we always are looking for uh is in in a
sense we're governed by
some instead of a heart
a hard wired a hard coded um
instincts and
we're looking for a zero sum now and
we're looking for
fast money and and then you get
really totally scared when things goes
against you
so that's basic sense of agreed and fear
would always enjoy uh drive the
financial market up and down
particularly when it comes to money
humans are very
funny it tends to evoke
the primal part of human nature
and so so particularly relates to
financial market and security market
money that that
human tendency of the extreme
instincts become more amplified
and more extreme and that's why the
financial market from the very beginning
has always been characterized by moon
and bust and what remains so now how do
you deal with
uh such a environment that will be
constant
well one way to deal with that is to
anticipate that
always on the corner at all times and
that's basically our attitude
that financial crisis will happen all
the time
people will always be driven by fear by
euphyrium
by uh i mean by by
this extreme kind of up and downs
and so we're looking for businesses that
are capable
of looking at leaning through that
and even businesses that could really
thrive in that
environment it says have a certain
characteristic of anti-fragile
and so so
that up and down becomes somewhat
friendly for us in the sense that
when our favorite company is on sale you
know discounted by
50 60 70 if we have money
we'll buy more of it if we don't have a
money it's
it is a hallmark of a good investor you
can
sit through watching your portfolio down
by 50
and not being affected at all on the
other hand
other side of the coin is that you're
equally unaffected
when everybody around you are making
fast money
fast and furious a lot of them now
you're really
seemingly totally left behind so
and that's really part of the
temperament that most
people don't have and that's why not
everybody can succeed
in this game of the investment and so to
succeed in this game
and require certain temperament and a
certain
understanding of human nature also
a certain common sensible approach
and knowing that they will invest in
return eventually
will mirror the actual business return
by actual businesses you know we know in
real life
real businesses don't really change by
day by hour by week
by month it took years for them to
really
either go up or down and so you should
expect your investment
without the coming over slowly gradually
over a long period of time so the
short-term phenomena should not really
impact you as much either on the upper
or down
and so if you have that basic
temperament
and basic approaches what you're going
to find
is that both of the euphyria as well
as the crush actually can serve you well
and this is really going back to ben
graham's basic concept
of mr market that is there
to serve you not to instruct you except
the real game of the investment
those phenomena both on the up and down
tend to be quite extreme
and testing and so the other thing that
will be very testing
is that you really do need to understand
uh the business itself
and if you really try to pretend you
understand
and you're really driven by something
else other than deep understanding
you'll be tested and so that's the
salient nature of the of the financial
market and sometimes they almost
feel that uh they existed they're too
really
to catch human weaknesses uh
that if you really don't understand
something that you pretend to
you will be busted at some point um
but if you truly understand you will be
able to add
when the security is really down
50 60 70 yeah can i actually
um talk a little bit about a specific
example there and
maybe get you to talk about an example
because one of the things that you
talked about was the stability of these
companies
and their managements in the face of a
crisis so crisis tells you a lot and the
one company that obviously
recently has done extremely well and you
could see it
is john deere so if you looked at john
deere in 2000
demand fell by 5 and their profit
margins fell to zero
if you look at what happens to them in
you know 1314
demand falls 35 and their profit margin
stays at roughly half what it was before
which is higher than it had been
historically
so clearly that's a company that's
changed and in the face of
sort of catastrophic uh external
conditions
has gone from doing quite badly to doing
much better
do you have examples of that from the
companies you've invested in
where you've seen them perform through a
crisis
i i do
my 27 28 years of investment that's
the kind of things you'll collect uh but
normally we don't talk about uh specific
companies
but could you share maybe a historical
experience of that so that the students
in the audience
might have a sense of what to look for
and looking for this stability
well bruce we tried this multiple times
in your class i know
i'm gonna change it very familiar to me
and there is a simple logic reason why
we don't do that
once you achieve a certain uh notoriety
uh in a certain field uh the people tend
to really copy that and that's not
the behavior we want to encourage uh
instead of gaining people fish it is
much better to really teach people how
to fish
okay so let me do one last question
do you prefer to be a generalist or a
specialist
investor and would one work better in
the chinese right
in the chinese market than another well
in a sense you always want to be a
generalist
uh in terms of a student of businesses
and you're interested you know you have
to have uh
to be good at this game you have to have
the innate intensive curiosity about the
business
all kinds of businesses it doesn't mean
you're going to really
really get to the bottom of it
oftentimes you don't
if you're honest with yourself but by
the time you really get into the
companies you really decided to invest
you really better become
a true specialist and to the point you
really know
hopefully better than anybody in the
world you can find
including the top management team and
the top management team because they
manage
the company they tend to be deeply
personally
vested in their own biases and may not
be able to look at the business
as objectively rationally as you do
so that's a really test so you want to
be a true
specialist in the company you chose to
really invest
but you want to be a generalist always
of business in general so that your core
covenants your circle of confidence can
constantly be
evolving and the enlarging over time
if i still really know what i knew when
i started when i first took your class
where when you first invest with me
we were not really anywhere near the
results
and we both joined so luckily
that that we continue to expand and we
continue
to learn but on the other hand it is
fascinating
to see that how business evolved over
the last
few decades will continue to evolve in
the next few decades
and that really makes me feel that boy
i'm lucky
to choose this field that i get paid
to really satisfy my curiosity and to
learn
all these great people and great
enterprises serving society
so i feel happy every day doing what i
do
well okay so let's talk about the
evolution of markets and in particular
at a 2010 panel at columbia business
school you mentioned that asia's role
in the global financial system was
becoming increasingly important
looking back how has asia's mole evolved
in the last 10 years and what about
china's role going forward in both the
world's business economy
and in the financial well
the word is a turnover exactly as we
predicted in asia
indeed to become a lot more important
particularly china in it
become even more important as i look at
in the next few decades i would say that
the chinese
market and asia in general will become
even more important
the set of dynamics that already set in
place
will continue to play off in a robust
way
so the chinese security market
in general and asia economy
that will become increasingly a very
very important ever more important
component
of the global market well all right so
let me give you some data that i don't
think is widely appreciated i mean the
chinese numbers are obviously
very difficult to interpret at least the
official numbers
and whenever you see that from a company
the data you really want to look at is
the data where there's a reliable
counter
and the trade data is where there's a
reliable counterparty because every
chinese export
has to be an import from another country
and every chinese import has to be an
export from
another country over the last eight
to ten years china trade
has grown by only about two and a half
percent a year
that's less than one percent faster than
u.s
trade what does that say about chinese
growth i mean that's clearly much slower
than the trade growth
prior say to 2010 2011 uh
and it's if it's fluctuated obviously
but if anything it's been slowing down
what does that say about china's future
well it tells you that the
characteristic the chinese economy
has changed fundamentally you know up
until 10 years ago
what really propels the chinese growth
is
has been uh was uh
international trade uh to a certain
extent
and i would say back in 2010
uh the net trade
a meeting the export import netted out
was
roughly about 9 of gdp
and so china's economy was heavily
dependent
on the global market now what happened
is
that and they were growing at really
double-digit
growth at the time when the rest of the
globe
global economy was growing at
much much less a fraction of that and so
at a certain point once you become the
largest treaty
nation uh you can't really the rest of
the world wouldn't be able to keep up
and the other thing that is happening is
after the
citizens become middle classes
their demands changes from basically
just
work saving too into
really work and saving and consume and
it's just also human nature
so roughly around 10 years ago as you
point out
the chinese economy has slowly evolved
into more of a consumer consumer-driven
economy
to the point that interestingly last
year was a
watershed year in a sense that the
retail sales the total volume
of retail sales for the first time
overtaken the united states
china was at the largest retail market
in the whole world at a six trillion or
so
us dollars the u.s is roughly 5.5
trillion now
granted that that was a special year
in the sense that uh the global pandemic
ahead other countries hotter than china
it's also said that china have done a
better job
you manage the pandemic but basically
the trend is there
china is emerging to become the
most dynamic fastest growing
consumer market in the whole world
and that is likely to continue for many
many more decades to come and so that
really
make chinese even more attractive
to the global economy in terms of people
who want to sell it
back to the consumers the middle class
in china and the characteristic of the
economy would change
and would also really provide unique and
interesting opportunities for global
investors
let me just talk a little bit about that
i mean the
thing about retail sales is that it's
selling goods
the thing about the developed economies
is that they're overwhelmingly service
economies they're not goods economies
and on that dimension it doesn't look
like
china's doing particularly well and as i
say
the export data you could understand
that that would slow down
but the fact that the import data has
slowed down just as much or more
tells you something about the nature of
domestic growth in china
what about the challenges in the service
sector in china
well you're certainly right that at the
current
stage the surface sector has yet to
become
as powerful and uh dominant
as most of the mature developed
economies in the west
and that's really amazing real set of
opportunities right
for the decades ahead of them and that's
by the way
not that much different than all the
other developed
economy and a comparable stage of the
development state
at ten thousand eleven thousand dollars
per capita gdp
which is where china is today and but
even look at the underlying
dynamics of the various different
businesses different performance
and those consumptions retails and the
service
are basically the ones that growing the
fastest
and overall trade internationally still
growing at a robust rate
but not nearly as much as the domestic
side of the economy
and so that's why the their share of the
gdp has gradually began to shrink
so domestic consumption becomes far more
important
both goods and the surfaces as we point
out
and so that just tells you that a
different stage
of the economy where it is today so
where do you see the unique challenges
and opportunities instead of finding
value investment opportunities
in china well uh
the china remains uh i think
one of the best market uh if you're a
valuable investor
um in many sense in a sense and the
market is still somewhat underdeveloped
the market today is not as
representative
as the real economy the way for example
united states
and so there's a lot of development in
that regard
and the trading and the investors are
still not as mature
and there's still a mentality of a fast
trading high turnovers which actually
renders some of the companies
again going through a faster pace of
this boom investment
again that usually provides bad
opportunities
for those mature patient investors who
truly know
what they're doing and also as you said
the service sector of economy
when it comes to financial services is
still yet to be developed
and china was really right at the stage
when the financial service industry
actually
is about to take off in a big way for
many reasons
and it just so happens also the chinese
government is quite a kin
in making macroeconomic policies
quite conducive for the development of
the financial service industry
and they began to open up to the global
firms as well
in a way they have never done that
before so all those
confluence of uh factors
really make the market that much more
attractive today than it was before
yeah can i say something about that
financial services is probably the fifth
and sixth largest service sector
the biggest is housing by far the second
biggest
is medical care the third biggest is
education
and the fourth and fifth biggest are
like wholesale and retail
distribution and personal services and
then financial services although in the
us
it's a little higher than that what
about those sectors in china
that sector is also growing right but
do you see opportunities in absolutely
we do housing
we see an opportunity shelter support
basically uh
virtually every industry are going
through a robust
uh uh growing stage um some more than
the others
and even if the industry they're now
growing as a fast
because you'll find interesting
companies values
and i don't have to you're the boolean
for this field
and so different people tend to focus
different aspects of
the industries and different aspects of
the growth profile some
looking value and high growth companies
some looking
values that moderate growth companies
some
outlook value in places that doesn't
grow at all
in fact they're probably declining and
they're able to find even bigger markets
so
if you are a true uh uh good investor in
the sense
that you can find a bad in everyone but
you probably
more capable of finding values
in a dynamically growing economy such as
china they're still growing at a
multiple times
of the mature economy in the west and
there's still enormous amount of
inefficiency
in this security market so that
combination of those two
really make it enticing on top of that
one
whole series of government report i mean
government reform
will make those inefficiencies gradually
be more efficient and so that transition
offers even more interesting
opportunities so this is this is a good
time for global investors and certainly
for
us investors as well okay in those
terms that as chinese financial markets
are developing
do you have certain reforms or other
things you'd be interested in seeing
implemented do you sort of have a
top development that you'd like to see
happen in the china
financial markets or even in the china
economy well in the sense it's already
happening
that's what i mean that the chinese
government and regulator
this in the development of the security
market
for years and years the chinese security
market is not very representative of
china's economy
partially because it really the uh
the ipo rules are based what they call
approval model uh you have to go through
lenses of approval layers of approval
process in order to be
enlisted and so the wild and bustling
are the ones who will be proved
by government for whatever reason
sometimes
often not really market driven compare
with other markets such as the united
states
that it is based on the gradual
situation based
and so as a market rhythm as a result of
the financial
market and security market here are
quite representative of the true economy
and as the chinese economy moving from
a export import driven economy
into more of consumer demand economy
the entrepreneurial companies with
market
driven dynamics are increasingly play
a larger role and therefore this
financial market have to reflect the
change in dynamics and china that the
chinese government is determined
reform is uh ipo process
from one of approval process model
into one that is much like united states
of
registration based model and so
we are probably still early in that
process
but as that process began to play out
and we will see
the financial market become more
reflective
of the real economy and the other big
changes that is happening is
that most of the financing are done
through the banking sectors
up to the point you know 80 plus percent
and over time the financing
is best to really do
through what they call direct financing
mostly through market driven dynamics of
fixed income equity and central social
and so we see the overall financing
model the chinese
economy from one that is more indirect
into more direct and so thus
is the reason for opening up this
financial service
company a financial service industry
both for domestic players
and global players as we're seeing that
dynamic plays on it over the next
decade or so there will be a lot more
opportunities
and the financial market will become
more mature there will be more
institutional players coming into it
and the financial market science will
become
much much bigger than what it is today
so those are really all bold well for
investors who truly understand what
they're doing basically in china
yeah let me ask another question in that
connection i mean the thing about a
service economy
is that services are overwhelmingly
locally produced and concerned
there are very few global universities
for example there are very few global
high schools
very few global hospitals um
that means that typically if you look at
developed economies
like united states with big service
sectors
the firms which tend to be local the
service firms that tend to be local tend
to be locally financed so i
assume you know that local banks in the
united states are much more profitable
than the big global banks do you see a
comparable trend developing in china
that you can take advantage of
some and some years and some know i
wouldn't say that to the
local banks in the u.s no but i'm just
thinking in terms of
local experts within china and
local service businesses that would
include of course local banks
yeah well they tend to really know the
local area
but the chinese regulation of banking is
slightly different
so there are only roughly about 15 bags
that really have
the mandate of being able to take
deposit on a national basis
and all the other rest of financial
institutions
are able to really take deposits in a
very very small
defined well-defined local region under
their town
villages cities it's very special and so
the it is a heavily heavily regulated
businesses and so that really gives them
almost oligopoly type of a status in
terms of
taking deposit which is very important
of course in terms of the source of
capital
so that dynamic is slightly different
than the united states for example
that the license uh
ability to really be able to open the
bank is
much much more relaxed in the united
states
than in china as a result
the the basically the dynamics
of the larger national versus local or
regional
banks and other financial institutions
are more driven by basically the
business dynamics the market dynamics
and this is very different than in china
it is driven first and foremost by
regulation
regime and so that makes
the uh a comparison uh of the banks are
really quite different
uh in china than the united states
so would a somebody investing in banks
in china have to be an expert in chinese
regulation
absolutely specialist
[Music]
[Laughter]
if you don't decide to team us anything
i recommend
you better become the most knowledgeable
on the planet before you really
interested really invest in
all them through the up and downs and
thicken things
and if you do understand them they are
good
it is far more profitable to own them
over the long period of time
okay so why don't we talk more broadly
about new trends in
value investing so among the many
popular and up
rising technological fields such as 5g
bitcoin ai have any of that
has any of that attracted your interest
as a value investor and why
well as i said if you're a investor
you really want to find out
what really influenced the change of
your companies
if there's one big forces
that are really quite prominent is the
fast acceleration of technological
changes and of course you need to
be well aware of those mega
technological trends
um it's this current wrong in wave and
that started
uh call it you know 40 50 years was the
invention of the semiconductor
particularly
the integrated circuit uh that really
ultimately
led to a personal computer and the
computation collaboration the
computation power
uh to ordinary citizens and from there
there's also the evolution of
communication technologies
and then the invention of the internet
uh somewhat
25 30 years ago from there the mobile
internet
so the intersections of compute as well
as
in the omnipresent and uh
instantaneous basically communication
really led
uh to this new phenomena of artificial
intelligence
and the data economy as a result of it
and so
this wave of technological change over
the last
40 years has fundamentally altered
the business landscape of all kinds
basically
and so whatever kind of investor you are
we do need to be aware of that huge
changes
and how do you deal with that in a sense
what you're
investing in businesses that are either
well insulated from those technological
changes
or in companies whose management
management team are quite capable of
adaptive
to those technological changes better
than their competitors
or in companies that are leading those
changes or enabling those changes
so that those changes are really on your
side
basically so
now do you have to be a true expert
to the point of an engineer i don't
think you do
but you you do need to be broadly aware
all those big technology changes now if
you happen to be a venture capitalist
in those who feel it of course you do
but if you're
a generalist and study all the
businesses
you need to be aware of those trends how
does it really impact
in the industry and the companies that
you're investigating
so so we are still
uh really at that in the middle of that
gigantic wave
that started with the invasion of
a semiconductor by the way you know when
the transistor was indented
well that's a longer i know yeah that
was 1942
yes yes yes and the first person i
1961 yes yes i'm
referring to the time right you get
uh integrated into industry and so
that's you know that really started this
whole revolution
that we're actually still in the middle
of it and
the current uh wave of
neuron network based artificial
intelligence is just kind of
the recent iteration and
the data economy uh that as a result of
it
is the newest adaptation
by industries in response to that
new technology and we're going gonna see
more of it
as time really began to evolve from here
do you see opportunities to invest in
new technologies do you have an example
maybe
in your past where you did invest
successfully in a new technology
we have in a sense back in in the days i
was trying to really
learn about businesses i invested in a
number of startups
and so i i am fascinated about the
technologies
um and today we have somewhat
uh smaller exposure to that
but but it is it is fascinating it's not
really you're not
interested in technology it's just it's
not that
easy to predict or impact because of the
pace of a change
it does require a different aptitude
different domain expertise
and the other thing is we just have
other set of
easier opportunities we just happen to
be lucky
[Laughter]
yeah well all right so let's talk about
a specific example a lot of smart people
believe that renewable energy
is the next big revolution and you've
done a lot of work
on battery technology and byd
so is that something that you think
about beyond batteries
what's your outlook for the electrical
vehicle industry say in the next five
years or is it
overheated now where is tesla going
[Laughter]
so the car industry is simultaneously
kind of being impacted by you know
four or five big mega trend the
electrification
the right sharing and the autonomous
driving
and the intelligent design all of those
really going into
the industry simultaneously
and so that really had attracted more
entrance
and that really heated the competition
also against the broad background of
uh climate change current uh
carbon neutral revolution in the sense
so
uh as a result the industry that really
haven't lasted for 100 years has really
turned being turned upside down on the
other side
it is a gigantic industry so other than
housing is probably one of the biggest
industry
and so the price is also big in the end
in the process though the competition is
going to become
very very intense still you know
it does still have that uh
characteristic of being
a scale economy as we talk about at the
beginning
of our dialogue um so
the survivors or the winners do
need to have a certain uh scale
in order to really to win in the end and
so
it is still early to predict who will be
the ultimate winner
but it is not early at all to predict
those mega trends are here to stay
so five years there will be far more
electric cars sold we have seen the
european countries began to declare uh
a deadline to stop basically
gasoline-powered
cars china is following that up
i think in dual course that we were
going to see those magnitudes here to
stay
and five years from now that trend will
become even more prominent than what it
is today
but it is very difficult to predict
the ultimate whenever any continue to
attract a new entrance at this point
but i do think that the ones that really
precise unique
technology have the scale
and have the right strategic
would focus do well do you have a sense
of which companies those are
well i bashed one so
so i like my money speaker itself
but we're not going to be the only one
that's a ruby fuel but
it is a gigantic industry okay
so in terms of
value investing education you actually
played a big role
in promoting and advocating
value investing from the books to
actually you underwrote in this class
that we talked about where i went to
beijing university and i think it still
survives
what's your vision for the kind of
education
that a new investor should embrace and
where that education might be available
well first of all thank you bruce for uh
come to uh
teach at the beijing university value
investing classes
that my colleague jeanne channel and i
started
uh six years ago and now is six years
still running and running farewell
and you have played an important role to
that and i think our
original inspiration for that class was
really based on pretty much your class
and your classes are pretty much
inspired and the continuation of the
bank
and ben graham's class graham and don
and
which had among others
warren buffet as student and i'm your
student
there'll be many more much brighter
investors coming after us and that's a
good thing
uh so we're trying to really do our part
to really to pass on those that we
philosophy the thinking
and the practical parts of value
uh to the uh to the next generation
in a sense uh so
in terms of like younger uh students
where you started today
so i think a few things will be
important um
when i when i talk to young students and
people who started out
um trying to get into the field i say
several things that's important
and you to always adopt a owner's
mentality
and so i like to really ask a
young student or an analyst or a firm
basically to imagine
all of a sudden that one of your unknown
uncle died and handed over
100 ownership to the company to you
and that's the business you're going to
study so any company
think starting point that way and once
you're really
kind of a thinking your own 100 percent
of it your mentality is totally
different
so you never know that business existed
now you're 100
and you have no idea how to run it you
don't know the people will run it
what do you do you want to know
everything everything you can possibly
get your hands on
and a lot of the things you know you
don't understand you just know the facts
you don't understand it but that's okay
you're going to continue to learn
until you get a hundred of it and even
if then because of the constant change
you're going to continue to evolve your
knowledge of it
now if you adopt that mentality study
any businesses
you have really started the process of
becoming
real valuable investor so that's the
first thing
the second thing is you really want to
maintain
intellectual honesty and that is
very very very important you have to be
really honest of what you know what you
assume
would you pretend uh subconsciously
and what you don't know and how do you
really know
that one of the things that charlie have
talked about
that i think make the most sense is it
was that
i'm never entitled to have a view and
two
i could find the smartest people
on the planet who took the other side of
that view
and i can argue better that
opposition than he does and when i can
do
that i would be entitled to have a view
same thing and applies to
investing in a sense that intellectual
honesty
is a good life philosophy to begin with
it is a critical it is a vital when it
comes to investment
because as i said that the security
market almost exists to really point it
to really to find your weaknesses
your dishonesty your potential
um your bushy mushy knowledges
and if you do not really process that
fundamental attitude of intellectual
honesty you'll be destroyed at some
point during this
uh during your career by the financial
market it was almost designed that way
to catch you can i can i say something
about that because it was better than
designed that way
every time you buy a security thinking
it's going to do well
somebody else is selling you that
security thinking it's going to do bad
and vice versa and one of you is always
wrong
so you better be sure that you're the
one
that's on the right side of that
transaction well
it is there is some zero-sum aspect but
not
always oh no it's a hundred percent zero
sum
the average return to all investors
in any asset class and therefore in all
asset classes
is the average return to all those
assets it brings out just to take a
slightly different view
but i'm never going to argue against my
professors
i'm just going to say let's just agree
with disagreement
that's okay okay it is a fair point
it is a fair point another thing i would
say
is that you you want to really devote as
much time
as possible uh to a study
of the history of the businesses
and the history of a great businessmen
in the past
the more you'll study more companies
the better you are when it comes to
judgment
on good opportunities and the judgment
about the fundamental characteristic of
the company of interest in you
and so i see all three things important
to
start with the 100 owner mentality
to continue to train yourself to have a
high degree
of intellectual honesty and lastly
to be a really a thorough student
of the history of the businesses all
three things
are really going to be very helpful if
you are beginning
to get into the field of investment
or you want to really improve your game
so
that's the mice my advice doesn't
understand good advice i'm not going to
argue with that
when you look back over your own career
yeah
are there things that whether at
columbia business school or in your
career since then
you would have done differently that
would have helped you get to where you
are today sort of more quickly and more
easily
yeah well i look
back i feel i'm extraordinarily lucky
and i feel nothing but gratitude
i feel lucky to accidentally step
into uh buff his lecture
at your class basically the first time
he came
uh i feel extra lucky that uh
when i got into the business and
that in a striker relationship um
was charlie munger i feel
extraordinarily
fortunate to live in a period of time
when both united states and china of
going through a fundamental economic
growth and provide enormous amount of
opportunity
that i happen to really know both
marketing well and so
i i looking back my career but not
nothing
i feel nothing but really gratitude um
but in terms of uh on the
[Music]
on the on the on the transition from the
u.s to china
so uh i think a lot of people
such as myself included went through a
period of time to really try to
understand
the nature of the chinese economy and
the nature of the chinese market
the nature of the chinese company
investment in china's companies
so one of the key learnings that i have
um and it is not that obvious
is the role that the chinese government
play
in that whole question equation if you
have
been a successful investor in the united
states for example or in the developed
market
you tend to come with a set of
assumptions about
the role of the government and the role
of
the market participants and
when you really look into the chinese
market
that assumptions you will see a lot of
challenges
and so you might really from time to
time arrive to views
that are inconsistent with your own
experiences
partially because historically the
chinese government
and the u.s government the western
government perform a
very different rules and that's one of
the
key aspects of really investing in china
it really requires a much deeper
understanding
and also systematic comparison
to get rid of those biases and that's
why that
you can really get rid of this typical
global investor going to china either
bold ability you fear your enthusiasm
or basically pessimistic
kind of calming collapse of a china type
of a mentality
when things are not going too well and
so
that is the education the most of the
international investors particularly
when it comes to china
would have to really go through and that
is important
but bear in mind the other aspect
to understand the chinese economy
is that the nature of of
the modern economy
is its ability to generate sustained
uh compounded economic growth
something that is only recently
emerged as a human phenomena
and this is where we we talk about the
zero-sum
versus uh versus a minion type of
mentality
now for the longest period of time that
almost
all natural or human affairs
are characterized by cycles in a sense
that everything goes up cycles you know
born
always increased energy goes from
you know hot to cold things from order
to disorder
great business has eventually lost his
ash so that has been the nature of
things
and economy going through boom and bust
but what
something unique happened over several
hundred years ago
was the beginning of the industrial
revolution we began to see this
phenomenon
of continued sustained compounded
economic growth and that is
really when that value investing become
very important
and that's why you'll begin to have a
phenomenal record
such as the one produced by warren
buffett and now by a few
other people as well the basic
logic behind that as i said over the
long term
your investment return is likely to
approximate
the actual business return of the
company invested
and so the fact that you're capable of
generating that long-term result
is a reflection of a changing nature
economy
what really drives that phenomenon is
something
that is utterly fascinating i literally
spent
30 40 years thinking about that
until i think i come to a certain
knowledge i wouldn't say i really
don't know at all but i think what
really produced
that phenomena is is
a combination of free market
enterprise way of organizing social
economic affairs
and combine that one with the invention
of modern science and technology the
combination of those two
produced a modern
form of economy it is a paradigm shift
so what's happening in china is that
roughly around 40 years ago
china has really stumbled finally into
that
magic formula of free market
economy now with chinese characteristics
of course
along with modern science and technology
and any economy that
has really strike a court and
strike that magic magic formula began to
produce
a phenomenon of compound economic reform
now that has to combine
with the stability of overall political
environment
to allow the market to enforce that the
new
economy to really release that power
and that is when sustained
uh economic i mean sustained investment
record
can be possible in china it is
it's not always there it's not always
possible
and often it was a zero sum but i think
from that period
on that a sustained win-win type of a
compounded
investment return becomes possible
and i notice that i didn't really
include the
political component of it and
most of the uh western observers
believe that political democracy has to
be part of the
uh uh equation except they forgotten
that political democracy wasn't there
when that phenomenon began to take place
in
the west in fact the political democracy
happened
later almost as a result but not because
of it anyway so that is another
layer of understanding the phenomena of
the investment opportunities in china
it could be interesting okay so what
about
uh let's just talk briefly in these last
eight or so minutes about your personal
interest
so you've devoted efforts to improving
equality and welfare of
asian americans and given the recent
elevated attention on this community
what are you doing
and planning to do or think ought to be
done for that community
well i was really like many
people from the asian american community
and america that was just
utterly dismayed heartbroken
over the last year and a half uh that
particularly since the later years of
the trump administration
that get worsened because of the
pandemic that this new wave of
anti-aging and hate crimes
and by all statistics that incidence
of racial discrimination against asian
americans has
dramatically increased over the last
year and a half
and full variety of a different reasons
the pandemics and the trump policies the
u.s china tension
and the systematic historical route the
surface to say
that many people in the asian american
community are living in
fears literally physical fears today
after being here for so many years have
been such an important
part of american experiment uh
experiment
and you know particularly to the
chinese-american
community you know after 150 years it
feels like the chinese exclusion act has
come
back again so
so i've been thinking long and hard what
can we do
to change the paradigm now
i had a different experiences when i
came to
america i had a wonderful wonderful
experiences american embraced me
with open warm heart and i have gotten
an enormous
amount of opportunities by columbia
university
by all the great people that i met a
long ways
and by the the opportunity i was given
to
to be successful way beyond my wildest
dreams when i first took here as a
immigrant not a penny and no nobody
doesn't use speak the language
to be where i am today and so
one thing that i always believed about
america
is this i think america is not defined
by geography it is not defined
by race it is not defined
by culture not defined by religion
america is defined by set of ideas and
ideals
anyone no matter your race religion
culture background if you sign up to
that
set of ideas ideals can be
america and i was one of those who
believe in those ideas and ideas and it
becomes
successful in america and i wanted that
experiment to really continue
and obviously when you look at history
it was
never a perfect experiment um and it was
often marked by
the cleansiness sometimes actually all
right crew and malicious
if you think about experiences with
african-americans and all the other
minorities
but i think that america remains the
only country on earth
so inspired and such constructed
and for that experiment to continue
it calls constantly to our better angels
inside each one of us and to really
restrict the worst instincts of all of
us
and throughout a different period of
time people need to rise up
to counter those worst instinct and
fight them and
face them down and this is one of those
period
again so i think the entire community
of asian americans have to come together
the entire
american community need to really come
together to really fight
this wave of anti-asian discrimination
so along with the uh a number of uh
wonderful colleagues we are co-founding
a new national organization
whose mission is to serve asian
americans
in their pursuit of belonging and
prosperity free from
discrimination slander or violence
and one of the things that our community
needs is
is enormous amount of funding the
statistics tell us
that only 0.2
of all philanthropy in america goes to
asian-american causes and we want to
fundamentally change that
and hopefully with this new organization
new group of people
we really want to fundamentally change
that picture
and the other thing is that with the
global economy the center of the global
economy is shifting from the atlantic
ocean
to the pacific ocean asian-american
20 million strong are going to perform
i mean play a increasingly important
role
to position america as the new
pacific economic power and that group of
people more than other ones
if fully integrate as the very fabric
of american society could help lead
america
to better integrated with the rising
economic ties in asia
it's okay that's terrific it's a great
note to end on unfortunately we have
two minutes left thank you very much
for this really encyclopedic and
enlightening talk
i think i have to turn it back over
however to the mc for the last two
minutes right
okay because they're on the screen thank
you very much
wow thank you it's always a pleasure
thank you for really having that class
you know 28 years ago
i wouldn't i wouldn't know what i'm
doing today so thank you
okay go ahead
hello vivian i think i'm turning that
back to you
brilliant can you hear us thank you
professor bruce greenward
and mr lee lu for this valuable
conversation
this marks the end of this year's
columbia china business conference
in these four days of discussion we have
taken a journey
across various dimensions of china's
amazing development
and exciting future in an age of change
and opportunities our speakers have
given us a fascinating
glimpse of what's to come on behalf of
columbia business school
our conference team wants to express
sincere appreciation
to all the guest speakers sponsors media
partners
and faculty of columbia business school
this year's conference is generously
sponsored by
bank of china hayton international
securities
tiger brokers johnson and johnson and
haito global
we appreciate the support from our media
partners
including yahoo finance senior finance
tai chi maxine
barron's high social
club tencent video sub china and many
more so lastly
thank you audience around the world for
your time and participation
live from columbia business school in
new york city good morning and good
night and see you
next year we finished exactly on time
welcome to columbia business school the
very center of business
welcome to the next level of you the
columbia mba is more than just advancing
your career
this is about honing your unique
leadership style bringing your visions
to reality
and delivering them to the world you
will be the leader
you want to be you will be able to walk
into a room any room
and solve welcome to new york the global
business hub
where startups get their start business
thrives and game changing strategy
gets put into play you will have direct
access to today's influencers
the entrepreneurs of silicon alley the
wizards of wall street
the trendsetters of fashion avenue the
agents of change
welcome to a network a family of over 42
000 alumni
let the collaboration begin this is not
a sit
and learn environment this is grab the
reins and lead
you belong here
you